<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://pastells.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://pastells.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/><updated>2024-06-13T18:45:07+00:00</updated><id>https://pastells.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><entry><title type="html">Modelling of frequency-sweeping Alfvén modes in the TJ-II stellerator</title><link href="https://pastells.github.io/blog/2024/modelling_frequency_sweeping_alfven_modes/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modelling of frequency-sweeping Alfvén modes in the TJ-II stellerator"/><published>2024-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pastells.github.io/blog/2024/modelling_frequency_sweeping_alfven_modes</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pastells.github.io/blog/2024/modelling_frequency_sweeping_alfven_modes/"><![CDATA[<p><em>This post was originally written by <a href="https://fusion.bsc.es/index.php/2024/02/27/our-new-journal-paper-in-nuclear-fusion-on-modeling-of-frequency-sweeping-alfven-modes/">Mervi Mantsinen</a></em></p> <p><strong>Alfvénic instabilities driven by energetic particles pose a challenge to the efficient operation of magnetic confinement fusion devices.</strong> These modes can dispel fast ions leading to the introduction of significant heat loads onto plasma facing components and degradation of overall plasma confinement. One class of Alfvénic instabilities known as reversed shear Alfvén eigenmodes (RSAEs) are of particular risk in devices with reversed shear rotational transform profiles. Reversed shear configurations have recently been of interest because of their enhancement to confinement quality. With this in mind, further study of RSAEs is necessary.</p> <p><a href="http://10.0.4.64/0029-5515/54/12/123002">RSAEs, also called Alfvén cascades, were observed</a> in the <a href="http://fusionwiki.ciemat.es/wiki/TJ-II">TJ-II flexible heliac</a> in hydrogen plasma discharges with varying magnetic configurations. <strong>In <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1741-4326/ad1c93">our recent journal publication in Nuclear Fusion</a>, we simulate the cascade events using the <a href="ttps://doi.org/10.1063/1.1590316">STELLGAP</a> and <a href="https://doi.org/10.1063/1.3313818">AE3D</a> codes and study the relationship between the frequency of the modes that form the cascade and the minimum value of the rotational transform profile.</strong> The simulations predict the appearance of a cascade sweeping downward in frequency formed by a set of modes with poloidal mode number \(m = 6\), and toroidal mode number \(n = – 9\) when the minimum value of the iota profile is varied between approximately \(1.47 &lt; \iota_{min} &lt; 1.50\), which is corroborated by experiment. <strong>The results presented support the utility of MHD spectroscopy</strong>, a diagnostic tool whereby the temporal gradient of the frequency of an Alfven cascade can be used to determine the variation in time of the plasma’s rotational transform profile.</p> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/alfven_simulation_results-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/alfven_simulation_results-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/alfven_simulation_results-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/alfven_simulation_results.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="caption"> Simulation results shown in black overlaid with experimental spectrogram. Error bars assume ±10% error in density and ±0.005 error in iota. Reproduced from Fig 11 in A.G. Ghiozzi et al 2024 Nucl. Fusion 64 036005. </div> <p>The full journal paper written by Adriana Ghiozzi together with the <a href="https://fusion.bsc.es/">BSC fusion group</a> leader, Mervi Mantsinen, myself and collaborators can be found at the following link: <a href="https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1741-4326/ad1c93">A.G. Ghiozzi <em>et al</em> 2024 <em>Nucl. Fusion</em> 64 036005</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="physics"/><category term="fusion"/><category term="physics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Description of my latest paper on Nuclear Fusion]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Depth Up-Scaling</title><link href="https://pastells.github.io/blog/2024/depth_up-scaling/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Depth Up-Scaling"/><published>2024-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-01-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://pastells.github.io/blog/2024/depth_up-scaling</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://pastells.github.io/blog/2024/depth_up-scaling/"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://arxiv.org/abs/2312.15166">SOLAR10.7B</a> paper introduces Depth Up-Scaling (DUS) as a competitor to mixture-of-experts (MoE). It is based on a simple idea: take an existing model, double its layers, and continuously pretrain it so it gives better results. The problem lays in the concatenation of the last layer of the original model with the first layer of its duplicate. The “layer distance” is greater than 1 at the seam where the two models meet. To make it easier for the resulting model to be continuously pretrained, the authors remove the final \(m\) layers of the original model and the initial \(m\) layers of the duplicate. Using this techinque, after the concatenation, the model suffers an initial performance drop, but rapidly recovers during the coninued pretraining phase.</p> <p>Although the authors don’t mention it, removing the inital and final layers makes sense from a mechanistic interpretability point of view (see the <a href="https://transformer-circuits.pub/2021/framework/index.html">transformer circuits thread from Anthropic</a>), given that the first and final layers have specialized tasks.</p> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/DUS-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/DUS-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/DUS-1400.webp 1400w," sizes="95vw" type="image/webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/DUS.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <p>The authors use Mistal 7B, with a 32-layer Llama 2 architecture, as their base model. They take \(m=8\), so that the resulting model has \(2*(32-8)=48\) layers. They do not try other options for $m$, so there surely will be improvements to the method in the near future.</p> <p>Nous Research has already trained a <a href="https://huggingface.co/NousResearch/Nous-Hermes-2-SOLAR-10.7B">Hermes 2 model on top of SOLAR10.7B</a>, and it seems to work really well.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="ML"/><category term="LLMs"/><category term="ML"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explainer of the Depth Up-Scaling method]]></summary></entry></feed>